Okay, so in this video, we're
going to be talking about another
important quality management
tool called Control Charts.
Now, Control Chart is used to show whether
or not a process is
stable and predictable.
It's used a lot in manufacturing and
medical devices and various other
industries, but always
it's showing whether
or not a process is
stable and predictable.
So let's just say we're in a
manufacturing environment,
and we are manufacturing
some drink bottles, right?
We've just got some bottles and we're
manufacturing these bottles.
These bottles are coming out of a
production line.
And they all have to be a certain height.
Let's just say for the sake of argument,
maybe 20 centimetres.
As long as they're exactly 20 centimetres,
then that'd be perfect.
However, they won't be exactly 20
centimetres.
Some of them may be slightly above,
maybe slightly below.
But as long as they're within an
acceptable limit, then we'll say,
you know, that's fine.
That'll be acceptable to us.
So, let's say they're 20.01 centimeters or
19.99 centimeters.
As long as they're within that range,
then, you know, we will be happy with that.
We'll be fine with that.
So we will plot our results in a control
chart.
So in a control chart, then, you have a
mean line.
In this case, our mean will be 20
centimeters.
Right.
So we're going to take a laser measure of
these water bottles, right?
These batches of bottles that are coming
out.
We're going to take a laser measure.
As long as they are, you
know, near 20, if they're on 20
centimeters or near 20
centimeters, then that'll be fine.
We're going to plot, right, we're going to
see some data points on the mean,
some data points above and below the mean.
As long as they are within an acceptable
limit, then we'll be happy.
Those limits are known as control.
limits.
You have an upper control limit and a low
control limit.
So in my example then, our mean would be
the 20 centimetres as I said, then the
upper control limit would be say
20.01 centimeters, low control limit 19.
99 centimeters.
As long as they're within the upper and
low control limit, all these data points,
as long as they're within the
upper and low control limit,
we will say that the process
is within statistical control.
And that's what statistics is The
statistical control means, it means they
are within the upper and lower control
limit.
Now the moment we see one single date
point, one data point either above the
upper control limit or
below the lower control limit,
then we will say that the
process has gone out of control.
So we have one batch of bottles that are
greater than 20.01 centimeters or less
than 19.99 centimeters, then the process
has gone out of control.
And in simple terminology, who needs to
investigate?
Basically, operator of the machinery needs
to investigate.
It could just be that the
machinery has gone out of
calibration, but they're
the first point of contact.
Now, there is another
limit that you need to know
about, something called
the specification limit.
So the lining green here.
They have an upper spec limit and a lower
spec limit.
Now, let's talk about where these limits
come from.
So the upper and the lower specification
limit, they are set by the customer.
That comes from the customer.
So think of that as the customer's
requirements, if you like.
Whereas the control
limit, the upper and lower
control limit, is set
by the process itself.
These are calculated by the team and set
by the process.
And the standard precision level that the
upper and low control limit are set at is
three standard deviations,
plus and minus three
sigma, plus and minus
three standard deviations.
That's the standard precision level.
Now, different organizations, different
industries may set it at different
precision levels, but for the
purpose of the PMP exam,
you need to know it's set up
plus and minus three sigma.
I had said that any data point within the
upper and low control limit, is within
statistical control, but there are
exceptions.
In fact, there are many,
many exceptions, but there's
only one exception that you
need to know for the exam.
These exceptions are known
as zone tests, and the only zone
tests that you need to know
is this one called the Rule of 7.
In reality, there's hundreds
of different zone tests, but
this is the only one that you
need to know for the P&P exam.
And what the Rule of 7 is stating,
it's stating that if you see seven
consecutive data points above
the mean or seven consecutive
data points below the mean,
then the process is out of control.
We need to investigate what's going on.
And the key is a word consecutive.
Seven consecutive above the mean or seven
consecutive below the mean.
Always look out for
that word or words that
describe that seven in a
row or seven consecutive.
Having seven data points above and below
the mean is acceptable.
Seven data points above and
below means you've got one
above, one below, one
above, one below seven times.
That's fine.
And that's what we're expecting.
It's when you see the word consecutive or
in a row, you know, worse to that effect,
seven consecutive data points above the
mean or seven consecutive below the mean,
then we need to investigate.
It could be that the process itself is
trying to set a new mean.
Seven batches of bottles have come out
that is above the, above the mean.
So it could be that the process is trying
to set a new mean.
It's trying to set bigger
and bigger bottles, or
rather it's trying to make
bigger and bigger bottles.
And eventually, if we're, If
you don't do anything about
it now, we might end up
going completely out of control.
So we need to investigate.
Now, just add on a couple of additional
terms here, any data points that is within
the upper and lower control limit,
these data points are known as a common
cause variance, also known as a random
cause.
So there's anything within the red here,
within the red line, upper and low control
limit, they're known as a common cause
variance or a random cause.
Any data point that is above
the upper control limit or below
the lower control limit, they're
known as a special cause
variance, also known
as an assignable course.
All right, so everything that you need to
know regarding control charts for the PMP
exam is pretty much on this diagram here,
right?
Now, naturally, I know
many of you that are
watching this video, you may use control.
charts in your day-to-day work?
I just know that you probably
know much more about control
charts than what you need
to know for the PMP exam.
But what I just said
here, this really is about
as much as what you need for the PNP exam.